Mario Vega: Hello, everyone. Let's give just a couple more minutes until more people join before we can start.
Mario Vega: Thank you.
Mario Vega: Okay, let's get started.
Mario Vega: I'm gonna share the agenda in the chat just now. Welcome, everybody, to ACDT number 99, today's October 5th, 2026.
Mario Vega: We have a small agenda today, consisting only of DevNet updates and mainly the Sepolia upgrade thing. We'll do the EL and CL breakouts, after that is finished. So yeah, let's just get started. On the first…
Mario Vega: Topic of the agenda today, regarding DevNet updates, do we have anyone from PandaOps that could chime in and share the latest updates of this?
Stefan Starflinger: Yeah, sure. I think,
Stefan Starflinger: The Shadow Fork updates would be most relevant now, that we ran last week.
Stefan Starflinger: Where we shadow fork Sepolia, and we did two rounds, and in the first round, we found some issues
Stefan Starflinger: Especially, with Nethermind, where the release didn't include some fixes yet.
Stefan Starflinger: And, Besu had some issues, where, there were empty blocks, that came from, peering issues on the Shadow Fork.
Stefan Starflinger: We also had, some issues with, ethrex, because the peering on ShadowFork is a little bit difficult.
Stefan Starflinger: And then there were some fork boundary-related, PTC issues and builder onboarding, that Lighthouse looked into.
Stefan Starflinger: And, figure it out.
Stefan Starflinger: And then in the second run, Nethermind went quite smoothly.
Stefan Starflinger: I think the builder onboarding also went well. We had also some deposits.
Stefan Starflinger: And, Overall, it seemed, it worked pretty well, and a lot of the issues are being worked on.
Stefan Starflinger: And we have Sepolia Shadow Fork, no Sepolia Normal Fork tomorrow.
Mario Vega: Awesome, thank you. Thank you, Stefan. Do we have, any comments? I think, in particular, from Nethermind?
Mario Vega: Yeah, EtherX and Lighthouse, do you folks want to chime in with any comments on this, or is everything resolved?
Iván | ethrex: I can start on the effects side. I don't know if you guys hear me well. I'm Masri.
Iván | ethrex: But…
Iván | ethrex: Yeah, the P2P issues we have are only related with this shadow fork, and shouldn't be a problem.
Iván | ethrex: Or tomorrow, or in the other networks.
Ben Adams: But never mind, it was fixed in our 2.1 release,
Ben Adams: 2.0 had some, some of the late ads to the ELS tests. We, we haven't included in that release, unfortunately, because they cut off
Ben Adams: And our QA was before that.
Ben Adams: Yeah, but they were already in our 2-1 release, which we intended to.
Ben Adams: Released before the Shadow Folks, but hadn't.
Ben Adams: And yeah, it's now available.
Mario Vega: Nice, thank you, thank you very much. Anybody else, who wants to chime in? Any incidents found or comments from other clients?
Mario Vega: Okay, I don't think so then. Stefan, anything else regarding DevNets? Anything that you wish to share, or…
Mario Vega: Let know, everybody.
Stefan Starflinger: I think that's mostly it. Yeah.
Stefan Starflinger: Possible, definite is… is down.
Stefan Starflinger: If you want to talk to that part of us.
Barnabas: Yeah, so I was just rolling out a new image update and, enabling QUIC on each of the CLs.
Barnabas: And,
Barnabas: Due to the fact that we don't have any supernodes online, we only had 100 validators on each of the nodes at reconstruction.
Barnabas: Didn't go as planned.
Barnabas: So, we ended up, going into different forks, and now, some of the columns are lost forever.
Barnabas: So, in the future, then that's where you're gonna make sure that we're gonna have enough supernodes on the network.
Mario Vega: Okay, thank you. Ben, do you want to chime in?
Ben Adams: Yeah, one thing about Sepolia, so I was having a look on ENR Scout to to check how many people were on the
Ben Adams: previous version, and not upgraded to 2.1, and I've noticed, at least for Nethermind, there's a lot of nodes that are on a very old version. So, is there any…
Ben Adams: Any way we can tell people to upgrade?
Ben Adams: I mean, they aren't on the version that even has the Sepolia, releasing it.
Parithosh Jayanthi: I mean, we can push on the validator chat a bit, but other than that, I don't know if there's any other way to convince people to update.
Łukasz Rozmej: They will notice tomorrow.
Mario Vega: Okay, great. I see people already chiming in with, updates to Sepolia, so let's just jump into that. I'll start by saying that, Sepolia upgrade is for Glamsterdam, of course, it's, less than 24 hours away. It's happening tomorrow.
Mario Vega: at 13, 13 hours UTC, with 53 minutes. So I just wanted to…
Mario Vega: See if there's any last comments from clients today. And I see already one from Prysm that they are going to be doing another release for Sepolia by James. James, do you want to just say that out loud or do you want to share anything else?
james: Yeah, this should be a patch release.
james: There were some last minute configuration issues that that were found.
james: For… for builders, and so for…
james: most nodes, it shouldn't matter, but if we're testing builders, we'll need to use the patch. And with this update.
james: It'll also include the partial data columns, by… by default, so I guess that would also be nice to test for the…
james: For the fork.
Mario Vega: Nice, thank you. Do you have a number of the version?
james: Yes, it's… I'll type it in chat, but it's, Version 7.2.1.
Potuz: wait.
james: And currently.
Potuz: Aren't we going to release 7.2.2?
james: 7.2.1.
Potuz: Oh, I just posted the wrong one on the Sepolia Validators channel. We'll change that.
james: Okay.
james: Unless we're we're doing a second patch, then it would be that. But
james: Our last release was 7.2.0, so this would be 7.2.1.
Mario Vega: Awesome, thank you. I'm glad that that got clarified today. Great. Alright, so I'm just gonna do a roundup of clients, just to check if any… if there's any other comments from clients. I'll start with the EL side of things. So, Geth, any comments for tomorrow, or…
Mario Vega: Version updates or whatnot?
Mario Vega: Rather just an acknowledgement that we are ready for tomorrow.
Mario Vega: If that's… if that's okay.
Mario Vega: Is there anyone from Geth in the call? Let me check.
Marius van der Wijden: Alright, so what…
Mario Vega: Just, just, readiness check, for tomorrow, Sepolia?
Marius van der Wijden: Yeah. Well, we've just had a new fix.
Marius van der Wijden: We have a release that is ready for Sepolia.
Marius van der Wijden: It would be nice to get that fix in as quickly as possible.
Marius van der Wijden: So, most people should be running with the fixed version, but yeah, there's nothing to stop us from
Marius van der Wijden: from using the old version for Sepolia.
Mario Vega: Alright, just to clarify, that fix is already out, or is it planned?
Marius van der Wijden: Yeah, it's planned, it's not out yet.
Mario Vega: All right, thank you, thank you.
Mario Vega: Following up with Reth, are we ready for tomorrow?
Mario Vega: I don't see anyone from Reth. I'll just skip them. Nethermind, you already said 2.1.0. Anything else you want to add or are we ready for tomorrow?
Ben Adams: I'm ready for tomorrow on that version.
Mario Vega: Okay, thank you. Erigon?
Mario Vega: All right, I'll just skip, Besu, any, anyone from Besuu? Do we have a readiness check for tomorrow, Sepolia?
Daniel Lehrner: Yeah, we already… I also checked our own validators on Sepolia, they're all upgraded, so… Should be good.
Mario Vega: Alright, perfect, thank you. And is ethrex everything ready for tomorrow?
Iván | ethrex: Yes, we are in a similar position as Geth. Today, there was something… there was some finding from Nico, from Lodestar, and we are working on the fix, but we should be good for tomorrow.
Mario Vega: Perfect. Excellent. I'll just jump into the CL clients now. Prysm, you already mentioned that you have a new version out or planned, but anything else?
Mario Vega: From you, from you guys?
james: I don't think so.
Mario Vega: All right.
Mario Vega: One question from Barnabas, will the Prysm release have the 200 million gas set?
james: Yes, so the… it'll have the scheduled, the Sepolia scheduled, Gas limit stuff.
Mario Vega: Awesome. Thank you.
Mario Vega: Anyone from Lighthouse?
Mario Vega: Any,
Pawan Dhananjay: Yeah, I'm here. We have released 8.3.0, release candidate 0, that's the one for Sepolia. The Pandas did find a bug in the Shadow Fork, because of which Lighthouse would
Pawan Dhananjay: Not,
Pawan Dhananjay: published proposal preferences correctly before the… just before the Sepolia fork, so we have fixed that on Unstable, but I don't think we, I'm not completely sure if we will do a
Pawan Dhananjay: additional release for that. The worst that will happen is that we just do local builds for the first epoch of Gloas, which I don't think is the worst thing.
Pawan Dhananjay: So… If we do another additional release, we'll just post it on the channels.
Mario Vega: Excellent, thank you. Also, same question for you guys, do you have the 200 million gas set?
Pawan Dhananjay: Yes.
Mario Vega: Awesome. Thank you.
Mario Vega: I'll carry on with Teku. Just release check any comments or anything from you guys. First of all, yeah.
Enrico Del Fante: Everything is fine. We have 96.9.1 ready for Sepolia. I'm checking right now if the gas limit is in. I will follow up on chat, because I'm doing this double check right now. I don't have it in my… right in my mind.
Mario Vega: And one comment from Barnabas in the chat. He says that he doesn't think that the Teku has a 200 million gas.
Enrico Del Fante: Yeah, because I believe we merged the PR, but it's not part of the… of the release, so I was checking if we were… if we merged it after of…
Enrico Del Fante: or before the release, probably it's after. But we are planning to do a release, but it won't go in, before Sepolia, so we won't release the .2.
Enrico Del Fante: So now it's believe there is an
Enrico Del Fante: You can, you can specify by, by command line anyway.
Enrico Del Fante: But we can follow up on that in chat.
Mario Vega: Perfect. Thank you so much Nimbus.
Mario Vega: Anyone from Nimbus who can get on.
Caleb: update.
Mario Vega: delivery.
Caleb: Yes. So, we are… we are ready. So, I'm just checking our latest release candidates, which is 26.10.0.
Caleb: And I think we are ready to go.
Mario Vega: Excellent. Thank you.
Mario Vega: Lodestar, anyone can give us a readiness update?
Nico Flaig: Yeah, all good from that. We have the gas limit as well. And, I'm planning to run a builder on Sepolia as well.
Nico Flaig: So if people want to connect to that, you can share the URL here. The only caveat we have on Sepolia is that it will not be possible to get them active at the fork, but I guess that is fine.
Nico Flaig: I let EF DevOps speak to that if we want that, but I think right now we don't want it, so…
Mario Vega: Awesome. Thank you. Also, same question, is Lodestar ready with 200 million gas limit set?
Nico Flaig: Yeah, with the guest schedule.
Mario Vega: Awesome, thank you. And lastly, Grandine. Do we have anyone from Grandine?
Mario Vega: I see a comment in the chat, we're working on some fixes, but nothing major. Current release version 3.0.0 is ready for Sepolia. And they have the gas limit set, perfect.
Mario Vega: Awesome. I think that's everyone.
Mario Vega: I'll circle around Reth. Has anyone from Reth joined who wants to chime in about readiness for Sepolia?
Mario Vega: Reth or Erigon.
Mario Vega: If not, we can sync, via Discord or Async.
Mario Vega: Great. I think it seems like everyone's ready for tomorrow. Do we have…
Mario Vega: Any other comments from clients? Do we want to discuss anything regarding tomorrow's fork?
Łukasz Rozmej: Let's go.
Mario Vega: Yeah, let's go. All right. Okay. Aw, Pooja. Yeah, go for it.
Pooja Ranjan: Thank you. It's not from clients. I think it's a special request for all the authors whose proposals are getting into the Glamsterdam upgrade. Since we are having Sepolia in less than 24 hours, I can understand the priority cannot be processed and making the PR, but once you are available, kindly take a look at it.
Pooja Ranjan: Ideally, all proposals should be moved to last call, because on testnet, we would want to have all the proposals on the last call. So I have added a comment, if you could make a PR whenever you get a chance, and if that is before the next EIP Editing Office Hour, please add your PR as a comment, and we would try to merge it before the next ACD call.
Pooja Ranjan: Thank you, Dean.
Mario Vega: Excellent, thank you so much. Yes, please take a look into this issue. Barnabas, please go ahead, yeah.
Barnabas: Yeah, I would like to raise one thing. So as Nico mentioned, we are not going to include any builders.
Barnabas: before the fork. This is due to the fact that we have a special deposit contract on Sepolia that is
Barnabas: Limiting us to the Peporia token, and
Barnabas: We basically just don't want to deal with making more deposits, validator deposits, to create the queue in order for us to have builders available at the fork.
Barnabas: We have tested this on the Shadow Fork, and it was actually working well there.
Barnabas: But for the fork tomorrow, I don't think we will be sending out Bapoja tokens to all the builders that would like to be participating before the fork.
Barnabas: So, what I would actually advise is.
Barnabas: If builders want to test this, then, to do that on Hoodi.
Barnabas: But yeah, everyone can just make a deposit immediately after the fork. That's when the deposit contract for the builders will become live.
Barnabas: And just normal Sepolia ETH will be sufficient there.
Barnabas: Oh, yeah, the deposit contract is already live, I guess. 2 weeks ago.
Barnabas: Nikki has deployed the contract.
Mario Vega: Awesome, thank you. Spencer?
spencer: Yeah, just a more of a question from my side. Just around versioning for testnet. So my understanding is that
spencer: We have the blog post with all the versions for all the clients.
spencer: But what's, like, the process that goes on, like, when there's a new version that needs to be bumped? And, like, how do clients actually announce the versions that should be used? And as a general, is this something that could be improved? And I guess I'm asking this now because…
spencer: Sepolia's tomorrow, and we have Like new version bumps happening, I guess, within the space of a day.
nixo: Probably bring pinging Alex.
spencer: So the blog post is like the default source of truth.
Barnabas: Yeah, I would say so.
spencer: I guess I'd ask as well, like, for me, if I'm updating my version, like, I would look at the blog post once and be like, it's done.
spencer: Is it expected for people to… Continuously monitor the blog posts.
Parithosh Jayanthi: I think it depends on maybe the network, so for Sepolia, we'd also be posting these updates on the validator chat, and you'd be quite sure that all the validators know about a version, so even a day is not too crazy.
Parithosh Jayanthi: For Hoodi, it's also roughly the same. I think majority of validators are on the validator chat, and everyone else would basically hear from either the blog or Twitter.
Parithosh Jayanthi: For mainnet, that's where it gets, I guess, a bit fuzzier, because there's no central location to coordinate people, so it would just depend on client release channels and Twitter and the blog posts and a combination of everything.
Parithosh Jayanthi: I think it changes per network, basically.
spencer: Thanks, yes. Sorry if that's a random question. I just figured it was, for me it was useful, so thank you.
Mario Vega: Nice, thank you. Any last questions, last thoughts or comments on Sepolia?
Mario Vega: From anyone.
Mario Vega: Alright, yeah, it seems like we are ready for tomorrow. Yeah, good fork, everyone.
Mario Vega: Yeah, I think that's it for today's, general.
Mario Vega: Call, and we are ready to go into the breakouts.
Mario Vega: If I understand correctly, Jihoon, are you in the call? You are leading the CL breakout for today, right?
Jihoon: So, Wilby, could you help with creating the breakout channel?
Mario Vega: The breakout channel, do you mean the call, or…
Jihoon: Yeah, they're cold.
Barnabas: We have another URL for that, no?
Mario Vega: Yeah, I think Pooja just shared the link. Perfect. Awesome. So everyone in the EL call, just stay here. We'll start in a bit and please everyone from the CEL jump into this different call.
Mario Vega: All right.
Mario Vega: See you, Seal folks.
Mario Vega: And I guess we can just get started on the EL topics. The first one.
Mario Vega: Was brought up by Maria. There's a message in… let me see which…
Mario Vega: ethereum magicians post that discussed the default execution gas limit for the ETH call RPC method. So, Maria, would you like to, go for this topic?
Maria Silva: Yeah, so this was, this is actually something that, is not a consensus change, so this is something we could do, without any consensus breaking, but essentially, and this was something that was only…
Maria Silva: confirming gas, so I don't know what the other clients did for ETH call. But essentially, for Geth, ETH call is, implementing the same
Maria Silva: Gas limit for execution as the, transaction.
Maria Silva: As the… the transaction limit, so the… the 16 million, gas.
Maria Silva: And essentially, there are, cases where people want to simulate calls that take more than the 16 million, Gazan for them. This is kind of, breaking their…
Maria Silva: their use case. So before ETH call was already… didn't have, the limit that a single transaction has.
Maria Silva: And so…
Maria Silva: the point here is that, so Gary from Geth already confirmed this and said he was fixing it in Geth. The question now is, like.
Maria Silva: What did other clients do?
Maria Silva: And, should we make it consistent? So my idea was initially to maybe add a comment on the EIP itself to describe that this should be the behavior for EIP call.
Maria Silva: But yeah, I would like to also see the opinions from the other clients.
Marius Van Der Wijden (M): Shouldn't this just be specified in the execution APIs repo?
Marius Van Der Wijden (M): I think that's at least, like, the place.
Marius Van Der Wijden (M): that this should… Probably be in.
Maria Silva: Right, so you say it doesn't make sense to be in the EIP.
Maria Silva: At all.
Marius Van Der Wijden (M): Well…
Marius Van Der Wijden (M): I'm not saying that, like, it can be added to the EIP, but I think the important bit is to add it to the execution APIs report.
Marius Van Der Wijden (M): Because it's, like, the canonical specification for the APS.
Maria Silva: Do clients have any comments here?
Maria Silva: Yes, so essentially I want to know if…
Maria Silva: everyone is okay with just keeping the current behavior of ETH call, because my understanding is, like, this would be changing it.
Mario Vega: Luis, if you're speaking, we cannot hear you.
Luis Pinto: I was waiting, I was waiting for you to give me a… Oh, sorry.
Luis Pinto: Okay, yeah, so I'm wondering, because if the maximum transaction gas limit is reached, what's their use case for simulating an ETH call that does not work on chain from now on?
Marius Van Der Wijden (M): It's, it's, it's, heavy view functions in contracts.
Marius Van Der Wijden (M): So, for example, there are some few functions that, that paint a picture of the, of the NFT, and so you want to be able to do that in the front end, via the deployed code, but you don't, like, you will never do this on-chain.
Maria Silva: Sorry, I would just add on that comment, on the EIPMA decisions, they specifically refer the, the.
Maria Silva: the renderers for, for SVGs, so what's the use case that Marius was saying, but also, like, quoters and, aggregators, so, yeah, but essentially, that's… that's the idea.
Maria Silva: Chase, to follow on your comment. So if Geth is implementing these in the right way, I would assume then that would be translated to the execution APIs.
Maria Silva: Report at some point.
Chase Wright: Yes, that's correct.
Maria Silva: Okay.
Maria Silva: Yeah, I posted on the AT37 channel on Discord, and Gary said I already have a fix for that.
Maria Silva: And it says it has a fix for ETH call, trace call, and ETH simulates. So, yeah, just need to make sure that it's included, but I'm guessing it should be.
Maria Silva: But I can follow through with that. Are there any more questions, concerns, or is everyone happy with this?
Maria Silva: Go, jochem.
jochem-brouwer: Yeah, so I'm reading this comment on magicians, but And…
jochem-brouwer: Does that not imply that we should actually change this API to have both state gas and execution gas?
jochem-brouwer: This is what we are proposing here.
Maria Silva: My understanding, maybe it's something we can double-check with Gary, but it's just the fix was just lifting the limits, not necessarily…
Maria Silva: Removing the two counters, but I'm not sure.
jochem-brouwer: Okay, because I think this is somewhat problematic, because, so for magicians, the thing is that for SVG vendors, so this is an execution, which needs, like, a lot of execution gaps, but for EVE call, we also have to, the purpose of EVE call could also be what would happen if I would execute this on-chain.
jochem-brouwer: So… That means that, a cow, which, on-chain would create, like, a lot of state.
jochem-brouwer: That would mean that…
jochem-brouwer: if we lift this limit, then the question is, okay, but how do we lift this limit? So, do we put all the gas in the execution gas, or do we put all the gas in the simulation… oh, in the state gas, right, but if you put… Yeah, it needs…
Maria Silva: It needs to be all in execution gas, because it's the one that can be used by both state and…
jochem-brouwer: Yeah, I see, I see. Okay, then, okay, then I think that's not a problem. Yeah, okay, sorry, yeah, thanks.
Maria Silva: Yeah, and I would say this behavior already happens today, right? Like, if you want a transaction that takes more than $60 million, it would fail. Like, the ETH call would execute and would be…
Maria Silva: Let's say, valid, but then you would actually submit the transaction, and it would fail, so…
Maria Silva: That is the behavior today.
Maria Silva: Okay.
Maria Silva: Okay, any more… Questions, concerns about this?
Maria Silva: Okay, if not, then I will reply on…
Maria Silva: It must magicians to communicate that, essentially, this would be fixed with an… with the execution API release.
Maria Silva: And I will double check with Gary, to see if the thing is already merged or not, and yeah.
Maria Silva: I think that's it.
Maria Silva: Maria, I don't know if there are any topics.
Mario Vega: Yeah, I think… no, there are not. This is the last one. I think we can… we can end the call here, then.
Mario Vega: If nothing else.
Mario Vega: Yep.
Mario Vega: All right, we can. We can end the end. The call, then.
Mario Vega: Thank you very much, everyone.
Marius Van Der Wijden (M): Thank you, bye bye.
Mario Vega: Wait.
jochem-brouwer: That's all. Bye bye.
Mario Vega: Goodbye.